today you're going to learn how to
actually use the heston model in the
real world and apply this under the
wrist neutral measure to option prices
so here we're going to go through the
math and we're going to explain the
characteristic function
for the semi-analytical solution we and
then we're going to actually implement
this in python and then we're going to
take that analytical solution
semi-analytical solution because we
actually need to
perform numeric integration on this
complex space and the way we're actually
going to calibrate our model then is
we're going to have all the parameters
in the hester model that we're
interested in and what we're going to do
is we're going to use an objective
function that minimizes the square
differences between our heston estimated
price with a certain parameter set
versus the market prices
so let's get into it so here we're going
to be using my jupyter notebook but i
have lent on a lot of resources to put
this together so we're going to be using
aspects of that as we go along so first
things first test and stochastic
volatility under the real world
probability measures you'll be very used
to seeing these equations by now and if
you've watched my past videos now the
thing that we need to do is we actually
need to translate this from the real
world measure to the risk neutral
probability measure and the reason we
want to do this we want to estimate the
parameters used in the risk neutral
world so we're going to use the option
prices to find the risk neutral
parameters so what we have to do to
actually translate from our real world
measure to our risk neutral probability
measure q is use the gerscino's theorem
now here on stack exchange someone
called kevin has gone through this
solution for us using gertino's theorem
so if you would like a detailed approach
on how to do that please take a look at
the link in the description so once
we've applied those translations we can
actually get our sde under the risk
neutral pricing framework so under the
queue probability measure so here are
sdes you'll note here that we now have
this new parameter called lambda which
is the variance risk premier so here you
can see our parameters in terms of the
real world parameters to the risk
neutral parameters and these will pop up
within our characteristic function so
just a reminder for all the terms that
are in here remember cap is the mean
reversion rate we've got theta which is
the long run variance v0 which is our
initial variance and then
sigma which is the volatility of
variance or the volatility of volatility
so here don't forget that we've got the
correlation parameter which is the
correlation between the two winer
processes between the returns
distribution and the variance process
so let's import some dependencies so
we've got
os we've got numpy pandas matplotlib
scipy integrate we're taking the quad
because we need to perform numerical
integration we've got scipy optimized
we're importing minimize date time now
we are going to be using end of day
historical information so this is an api
service so we can get a whole bunch of
um call options for the s p 500 index
really easily into python i'll show you
that later and we're also going to be
using this module here nelson siegel
svenson which is how we can actually
just calibrate the yields curve and get
the zero coupon rates
so
here i've drawn a number of academic
papers and online resources and all the
links are in the description below so
feel free to take a look at that
now the standard arbitrage arguments
that we arrive at from garmin's partial
differential equation here under the
hurston model is that we can actually
build a solution that looks a lot like
the black shoals model so here we have
the stock price times by this
probability one which is the delta of
the european call option and here we've
got minus the discounted strike with
this probability two which is just like
the conditional risk neutral probability
that the asset price will be greater
than k at maturity so both probably
probabilities 1 and 2 also satisfy that
pde with the characteristic functions
phi 1 and phi 2.
so these are known these are known in
terms of p1 and p2 and they're defined
in terms of in the inverse fourier
transform so if you manipulate the pde
in terms of the log of s so this x
prices this is how you arrive at this
characteristic function so what hurston
did is he assumed that the two
characteristic functions had this form
now there's a reason why he assumed that
but we won't go into that into this
video so if you go through and you solve
the pde then you're going to come up
with the analytical solution for these
parameters so we've got c and d in terms
of all the parameters below here and
we've got even parameters that they
depend on now for any help for going
through that entire process there are
quite a few papers here i recommend this
hearst and stochastic volatility model
implementation calibration and some
extensions by sergey milkerloff and
erlich nogle this is really
comprehensive and
it's very easy to go through the steps
what i will say now is that as soon as
you want to try and simplify it in terms
of one integral so remember we have s
times p1 minus k
the discounted strike times by p2 as
soon as you want to actually simplify
that formula into one integral that's
where i think that a lot of the online
resources have mixed up signs and made
small mistakes so it's really hard to
find
what is the true
one integral under european pricing so
let's take step by step through here and
let's try and filter out the correct
signs for this characteristic equation
so what we're trying to do is we're just
trying to add this fourier integral into
our call european call equation now
and what you what we can do is we can
obviously just take the s and discounted
strike out to the left hand side and
we're left with this fourier integral on
the right hand side now we've still got
our two characteristic equations and you
can see phi 1 and phi 2. so what we want
is we want one equation in terms of phi
and we want to be able to change these
parameters so they're not dependent on
the two states so the correct form for
phi is here and how did we get here well
essentially here there is no longer
changes with regards to b1 and b2
constants or u1 and u2 constants now why
is that between the two characteristic
functions well essentially let's explain
that when you rearrange the solution and
then you work out that b1 and b2 and u1
and u2 are no longer featured so if you
remember that this characteristic
component is broken down in c plus d
times v plus the complex number i
phi x well then remember that x is just
lns so what we can actually do is we can
work out that e to the power of ln s to
the power of i phi is actually just s i
phi
so what what does that mean well that
means that we can actually take that
down outside of our integral so now if
we just consider c we have this r phi i
tau
now we can immediately take that down as
its own exponent now for this component
here you can see that we have negative 2
ln so we have e to the power of an ln so
obviously what we can do is we can
multiply through this front term in the
exponent so that's a divided by sigma
squared so we get -2 a over sigma
squared and we put that up to the
exponent of the ln once you've got it in
this form then you can just bring this
whole term down so we actually have that
exponent one that we spoke about
multiplied by this entire term here and
of course what you're left is with is
the exponent which was this bj minus rho
sigma phi i plus d tau multiplied by the
alpha tau and sigma so in all the
solutions when these two integrals are
separated into p1 and p2 these fourier
integrals
um essentially you've got two solutions
for dj and and and gj in terms of b1 and
b2 and u1 and u2 and what we want to do
is we want to
create the one fourier transform so that
they're all the same under the same
equation
so this will make it easier in terms of
actually implementing and numerically
solving this integral
so how can we reconcile the difference
here well essentially all of this is
taken into account in the offset of this
phi characteristic function so our first
characteristic function becomes an
offset by the complex number one
compared to just the characteristic
function with phi now how can this be so
here i've got the math for understanding
the changes in that bj term and i've
tried to put an end then the uj term
respectively
in terms of d and i've tried to lay that
out
as succinctly as i can if you'd like me
further explanations just leave comments
in the section below and i'll try and
explain better there
so the first thing we're going to do is
we're actually just going to implement
this characteristic function in python
with all our parameter terms so here
we're going to calculate these
parameters here which are part of the
characteristic function dg a and b and
we're going to use them then to
calculate exponent 1 and then term two
and then exponent three so let's get
into the python so here you can see that
i've got phi and then all my terms here
so s zero v zero kappa theta sigma rho
lambda tau and r we've we're calculating
the constants a
and b
i'm combining this term called raspy
which is um just because it shows up a
lot so that's rho sigma times phi times
the complex number which is just i j in
python d is very simple all we're doing
is the square root which is just rho
sigma times phi times complex number
minus b all squared plus phi times
complex number plus phi
squared times by sigma squared
now
g is just in represented by b minus rise
pi plus d all over b minus rice pay
minus d
and then calculating the characteristic
function we just do it by components
again that was just exponent one term
two and exponent two okay now that we
actually have the characteristic
function what we can do is we can
actually define the integrand as a
function now you have to do this if
you're going to use a known numerical
solver like the likes of scipy so again
for the integrand here we have all of
our parameters and i'm actually
placing this all in terms of the args
which gets passed through to the heston
characteristic function
so here i've just got the exponential of
r times tau times by the first
characteristic function which remember
is just the offset by the complex number
and then minus k times the heston
characteristic function
we just phi in the denominator we have
the complex number um times by phi times
by k to the power of i phi
now
if you weren't going to use a package
like psi pi then we can actually perform
this numerical integration ourselves and
the easiest and simplest one is probably
one that you learnt in high school
mathematics which is using rectangular
integration
so this is where we're going to use the
midpoint to calculate
the height of the rectangle and we're
going to multiply it by the width over
this integration space so for
rectangular integration we've got heston
underscore price underscore rec we've
got all our parameters and again i'm
passing through args to our heston
characteristic function i'm doing the
same thing in terms of the numerator and
denominator as before when we defined
the integrand but this time i'm define
i'm going to step through the integral
with n steps so i'm taking 10 000 steps
i'm going all the way to 100 not
infinity 100 is plenty enough for the
types of integrals we're doing here
and i'm starting off with a zero price
the width of my steps is just going to
be umax so 100 divided by n steps so
here we're just calculating the
midpoint that we're actually going to
calculate fire by taking the steps and
then going through each time step and
then once we've got the midpoint we
place that into our characteristic
function and we offset for the first
first term by minus
the complex number and then in the
second term just pass in phi
so here each time we multiply by the
width times by the integral and what we
get is we're adding this to the area to
that price every time
once we've got that i can return just
the real component and we have p divided
by pi because that's what the integral
was divided it was divided by and then i
just need to calculate this half of s
minus discounted strike
so that's returning the heston price
using rectangular integration using the
psi prime and then we can actually use
that integrand function that we defined
i just have my args
i'm going to use sci pi integrate quad
function and i'm going to return the
real part which gives me the real
integral component and the error so i've
got quad which takes my function which
is the integrand and then i have what am
i starting with while i'm going from 0
all the way to 100 and i'm using my
arguments as all of these they get
passed through to my integrand function
and then in the same way i take that
real integral component i divide by pi
and then add
a half of s minus the discounted strike
back to get my heston price
so let's test that well essentially here
we've just got parameters to test
initial asset price and all the other
parameters in the hester model
we just use hest and price
using the scipy integrand function quad
and we can work out what our price is so
that's an easy implementation
now let's get into the crux of this
video where we actually go through and
get real options data so we can actually
calibrate this model so first thing we
need to do is get risk-free rate data
from the us daily treasury yield curves
now you can get that from this website
here
and essentially what you do is you can
just click here and then look for the
table for the daily rates and we have
that in terms of the one month all the
way to the 10-year tenures
so
once we've got that information
what we can do is we can get that in
terms of the maturities which is the
time in terms of years and then the
yields which was just the information in
the table
don't forget to get that as a percentage
so divide by a hundred then i'm going to
use something to actually bootstrap my
curve well we're going to actually use a
parametric approach here which is the
nelson siegel svensson model
which is just an ordinary least squares
approach so we're going to fit our curve
using calibrate nss ols and we're just
going to pass our yield of maturities
and yields in there so then we have our
curve fit for this model
and you can see all the parameters that
have been parameterized with our real
world data there
we need this because then when we have
options at all these different prices we
can just easily calculate what the
risk-free rate is at all those time
horizons
now for the of day historical data api
now
i have recently made a collaboration
with end of day historical data and
essentially what they are is that
they're an easy to use financial
software api that are across a large
name a stock exchange for all different
types of ets indices option prices real
time data intraday data etc now
i have a link in my description which
allows you guys to sign up here pricing
is actually pretty good so the all in
one package
which i recommend is the 80 one here but
again you can actually sign up for free
and then you'll get 20 api calls per day
which is nothing but at least to test
out
whether you're going to be using this
api or not
so again you can get a whole range of
financial data but i think one of the
best things is being able to call it for
options data
which is very very easy so as i
mentioned my link through to that is in
the description below but check it out
if you're interested in getting a cheap
financial api so here i've got my api
key and i'm i've just stored it as the
in the environmental variables and then
i associate my end of day historical
data module with the api key
so just initial initializing that class
and then here i'm getting a response
which is
a function called get stock options and
i'm just going to get the s p 500 index
option prices because i haven't defined
any parameters or dates essentially i'm
just going to get the latest bid ask
information last traded last volume and
all that latest information for prices
offered right now in the market once
i've got that response essentially that
end of day historical
class forms that into a dictionary in
python it's taken the json and formed a
dictionary for me and now i can just
index that dictionary for what i want
now you can take a look at the code here
and essentially what i'm doing is i want
all the strikes i want all the
expiration dates i want to set up
another dictionary where i then define
the strikes and the price for all the
call options so once we've got that what
i want to determine is that which
strikes across all these maturities have
actually been traded
so
if if i don't have products offered in
the in the far 10 years then i don't
really want to see them so i've done
this all strikes and i'm just comparing
the sets of all the strikes at all the
expiration dates i'm getting the common
intersection and then i can see that i
have 22 common strikes so once i've done
that i can set up a price and maturities
list and then i can work through all
these market prices in my dictionary and
and calculate the maturities in terms of
years and then i can calculate the price
from all the strike prices if they're in
that common strike list
once i've got my price array i work out
that i've got 41 by 22 so 22 strikes and
41 maturities
from there i actually want to decrease
that that horizon a little bit so i had
time all the way out to four years but
yeah the volume there necessarily wasn't
necessarily trading
or all that liquid so maybe not that
representative of the space that i'm
interested in calibrating my model so
i've just shown you how you can
subsection a data frame here so we've
taken this surface
as the data frame with our price array
indexes the maturities and columns are
the strikes and then i've just said i
only want the index if it's greater than
0.04
years but less than one and then also if
the strike's greater than 3000 or less
than 5000
and then i've just printed out my data
frame here so you can see what those
prices market prices in terms of index
points look like here for the options so
now what i want to do is i want to take
this
data frame and i just want to flatten it
so that we actually get a price for each
one of these corresponding maturities
and strike then once you've done that
what you're going to do is you're going
to create another column called the rate
which is where we take the maturity and
we're going to apply the curve fitted by
our yield curve so we're just going to
find out what the risk-free rate is
using our parameterized model
from nss to actually fit the risk-free
rate into this pandas data frame now the
objective function we're going to use
from this is from this paper here now
link in the description essentially
we're going to minimize the squared
errors but with a weight term and a
penalty factor so first off we're just
going to call this penalty factor 0
today but again you could come up with
whatever you want and for the weights
this is very crucial to how you actually
calibrate this model
for example you might want to put less
weight on less traded volume in later 10
years or wider strikes that will have
less volume traded
whereas we're not going to consider that
today um all of the strikes and tenures
that we've chosen in on those index
options are quite liquid and essentially
i'm going to weight them all the same so
it's just going to be 1 divided by n
times m which is just for every market
price
so here i'm just taking the market price
i'm going to calculate the heston price
with the parameters with a set of
parameters that we have and then i'm
going to square it and we're going to
take the sum over all those squared
errors
here my optimization my objective
function becomes
the parameters that minimize this
squared error over the entire set and as
long as i have parameters this u
parameter that's compact and in a range
that a solution exists i'm all good to
go ahead with the objective function how
do you actually implement this well
we're going to use scipy minimize so
first thing we're going to do we need to
define
what the actual starting index price is
and that's just from our json response
that we had before and it's the
dictionary the last trade price
then i've got my rates which is just
from my vol service long which is the
rate and that's to numpy float here i've
got my strikes again we're just going to
take that from our pandas data frame
we're going to take tau which are the
maturities from our pandas data frame
and we're going to take the market
prices from our pandas data frame those
are all floats we then have parameters
so the parameters we want to optimize uh
v0 kappa theta sigma rho and lambda
and here for sci pi you need your
initial guess so i've defined that as x0
and then we have a lower and upper bound
so here at the lower bound i've got
0.001
and with an upper bound of 0.1 and
essentially you can make this whatever
you think is reasonable remember that
row correlation can only go between
one and one and super values of lambda i
wasn't too sure but taking a look at a
range of academic papers um of which
i've included here on the website i
think minus one to one was fairly
indicative of that risk premier for
volatility
so once we've got that i'm just going to
create a list comprehension of my start
values and my bounds and i'm going to
define my squared error term so my
squared error term this is my objective
function i have x which is just all the
parameters so i have a list
comprehension each time full params in
param in x i just unpack the variables
and then i pass them in to my heston
price rectangular function i'm just
taking the price minus that
calculated price squared divided by the
length of that price series i'm just
using numpy sum to calculate the sum of
the error if you wanted to add the
penalization term here's where you would
do it
i descended i decided just to comment
that out in the end and then you would
return error plus penalty so to actually
execute this you just call scipy
optimize minimize which i just had as
minimized there we've got our function
we've got the starting values i have the
tolerance so how much i want to change
each of these individual variables by
what method i'm using
and essentially you're going to be
limited here
by actually having to include bounds so
only a couple of the methods you might
have to go take a look at the
documentations and here i'm defining a
number of max iterations so it doesn't
take too long as we run the result then
essentially we get our values back in
this x array
and here i can just
define those parameters
by unpacking them with list
comprehension
once i have that what i want to do is i
want to calculate these estimated
options and then i actually want to
visualize them on a surface plot so here
i can just use heston price rectangular
integration scheme using those variables
and then i'm just going to add that to
my vol surface long pendus data frame
that i had before
now the volt surface long i can then
print here and now i can see i've got my
maturity strike price rate and now my
heston price and you can see that the
heston prices are actually pretty close
so we do have some error but again we've
calibrated on 364.
rows
different prices different maturities up
to one year across different strikes so
that's obviously
pretty pretty good there so let's
actually visualize those market prices
versus
the heston prices we're going to be
using uh plotly here
so plotley i've got a mesh for my actual
prices for my market prices and then
i've got the scatter
3d scatter points for my heston prices
and here i'd find it's just useful to
visualize that in a plot
but essentially we've got the market
prices here is that blue mesh and then
my calibrated heston prices are the red
dots and you can see it's uh you know
there is some error in terms of point
values on particular
particular strikes and timelines but
we've pretty much got it bang on so
essentially that's how you calibrate the
hester model
for option prices european option prices
on the index so hopefully you got a lot
of value out of this to actually
calibrate a hester model
for american options we need to come up
with a finite difference scheme now we
haven't gone through that here on the
youtube channel so we're actually going
to take um a step back and start from
beginning of finite difference schemes
and then go through two more complex
applications of the likes where we would
actually be calibrating a hester model
to american prices
so hopefully you can use this code
and you can play around with it also i
really encourage you to go through the
math step by step
there are a lot of different resources
online which
may or may not be true with just changes
in differences in signs between those
different analytical semi-analytical
solutions i think the complication has
come about when you actually combine
both of those integrals into the one and
then you have to define your parameters
correctly so i think that's where some
of the signs sometimes get mixed up but
i encourage you to step through the math
line by line
on your own take a look at these papers
for uh help now if you did stick all the
way to the end i really appreciate you
guys sticking around i really want to
try and build my patreon community so
i've just started up we have a discord
channel and right now we have 50 members
where people are trying to participate
in active discussion on everything quant
finance so it only it's only one dollar
to sign up for the actual discord
channel if you'd like access to my
jupiter notebooks it's six dollars
australian per month but essentially i'm
really trying to get as many people as
we can to get across to this quant
community so if you're one of the people
that have stuck around to the end of the
video please subscribe to the channel
and join the discord channel to be part
of a like-minded quant community